Welcome to this 2026 release wave one
edition of what's new in the AL
language.
We're going to talk a little bit about
the language changes and the tools
changes in this release and then we're
going to talk about AI from an AL
developer perspective.
I know AI is super interesting, but
first let's go to my favorite editor and
look at some code.
Let's start with the continuation of our
JSON support.
We've now added the ability for you to
select multiple tokens in the select
token method.
As we can see in this line here,
I am now selecting a number of origins
into the result list.
If we go further down the list here, we
can see I get the list of routes here
into an array and from that array I can
even select the more complicated set of
my JSON objects here. Moving on to
something different, the
data transfer object has now a new
method called add destination table
filter.
With this method, you can now filter
what you want to update in a data
transfer.
In this case, we want to get all the
Copenhagen origins and we want to put
them into all the routes where the
routes are currently empty. Not all the
rows, but only the ones where the route
is currently empty.
This makes it much easier to do specific
targeted updates in a data transfer.
With data transfer, we also updated the
update audit fields method to now be
available in cloud. This means everyone
can now control whether the system
modified and other audit fields will be
updated as part of the data transfer.
By setting it to false as I've done
here,
the audit fields will not be updated as
part of this migration.
Another new language addition is the
ability to define and include analysis
views in your extension. You can now
ship analysis views with your pages in
your applications.
And now let's talk about namespaces. My
colleague Balazs will talk about what's
new in namespaces. As you all know, AL
namespaces are nothing new. We have
introduced them in version 23 and since
then it has been an active area of
investment for us. We have been
continuously adding tooling and language
improvements to make them better and
easier to adopt. In this In this
session, I would like to show you some
of the latest improvements we have made
to this namespace story.
The first area is making namespace
adoption easier. Adding namespaces to an
already existing large code base can be
a lot of repetitive work and we want to
automate as much of that as possible.
So, we have made the code action for
adding namespaces automatically
even
smarter. It now uses a three-tier
resolution strategy. First, it checks if
you have a namespace template set in
your settings.json. the parent folder
placeholder if you want to resolve the
namespaces using the folder structure.
In my In my case, it is set to my root
namespace.parentfolder.
So, if I go to the sales order sales
order.page.al file, which is in the
sales folder,
and invoke the code action,
it will add my root namespace.sales.
If there is no namespace template
specified, the second resolution
strategy will kick in.
It looks at all of the sibling files in
the same folder and tries to infer the
namespace using the longest common
prefix of their namespaces. So, in my
case, I have three files under the sales
folder.
One of them has my root namespace.other.
Next one has my root namespace.sales.
And therefore,
the third one will get the longest
common prefix of those two, which is my
root namespace.
In case there are no sibling files or
the sibling files do not specify a
namespace, we fall back to
publisher.projectname
like so.
And in this file, you can already see
the other area where we have made it
significant changes and that is
referencing objects by their fully
qualified names. We have extended the
object metadata model to carry the
namespace information all the way down,
allowing us to build a name-based object
resolution system in the runtime. Among
the first things benefiting from this
new system are handful of method
overloads for running code units, pages
and reports. So now, you can invoke the
run, run model and execute methods using
the fully qualified name string
literals.
We have also added support when it comes
to working with records. You can now
invoke recordref.open
with a fully qualified table name.
And the other going the other way,
we have exposed the fully qualified name
property on both records and recordrefs.
So, you can open records by fully
qualified name and you can retrieve the
name at runtime.
So, to summarize, this new system will
enable a bunch of exciting new features
in the future. So, if you haven't
started adopting namespaces yet, now is
a great time.
And now, let's turn our attention to
tooling. First, I would like to talk
about an alternative way of downloading
symbols.
I believe that all AL developers know
the pain. You have just opened up a new
project, maybe a completely fresh one,
maybe a newly cloned one, and you see
errors. The AL packages folder is empty
and you're missing a bunch of symbols.
Traditionally, you would have to go into
the launch.json and set up a connection
to an environment to get them. It can be
a real productivity killer. We want to
focus on development and spend as little
time on setup as possible.
Today, I will show you how we have
gotten rid of this friction. Let's jump
straight into it by running
the download symbols from global sources
command. After specifying the
localization, in a matter of seconds, it
will pull all of the symbol packages
directly from Microsoft public NuGet
feeds. No authentication, no
environment, no extra setup. Just your
extension and an internet connection. In
the background, it is resolving the
platform, application and all dependency
packages specified in your app.json and
also resolving their second level
dependencies automatically.
And since these are symbols only
packages, there's no IP concern either.
These feeds are not brand new
infrastructure. AL Go for GitHub has had
the ability to pull AppSource symbols
from these feeds already. What we have
done is surfaced the same functionality
directly in VS Code so you can benefit
from it in your local development loop
as well.
But what about my PTEs or apps not yet
published to AppSource, you might ask.
Using the AL.NuGetFeeds, you can specify
your own NuGet feeds and the downloader
will include these alongside the
Microsoft ones. These custom feeds take
priority, but if you want full control
over the source of symbols, you can
completely disable the Microsoft feeds
by using the use only custom feeds
setting. So, give it a try. One command
and you're ready to build. No
environment setup needed at all. Thank
you, Balazs. And talking about building
applications, we also have to test. We
now have the test execution built into
the AL language extension. Check out
this video on running tests from Visual
Studio Code where we'll go into all the
details and perhaps a few extra details.
We develop and test many applications in
the Business Central team.
So, let's check in with Espen on
workspace compilation.
Thank you, Stefan.
Last time I was I was here, I was
showing this slide. This slide is a
snapshot of our BC apps repo.
It is growing and it's already huge.
And last time I talked about how you can
streamline your builds with the
directory app.props.json
file.
This time,
I will talk about another problem we
have in this repo now. It takes a long
time to build.
Today, we are building this using the BC
container helper. It takes approximately
2 hours using GitHub runners.
Our system engineering team, they would
actually like us to do a little bit
better. So, we have looked at how we can
optimize the compilation process.
And I will show you what we did.
We have added some new tools to our AL
tool, AL alias if you're installing the
tools package.
And with that, we can do a lot better.
What I have here is a is a folder open
the folder with four
uh
AL projects in it.
They have dependencies. Right now,
there's only a directory app.props.json
file, which specifies the publisher
name, the version
and also the runtime in this case.
The runtime is new. I will get back to
that later.
But that right now, I don't have any
workspace file defined in this folder.
But I would like to have one so I can
build it fast and efficient.
So, I will use the AL
workspace
create command.
And I create a new workspace space
called Contoso
and I point it to this directory with a
dot. So, what it will do is that it will
search for all after JSON files in this
directory and below and create me a
workspace from it.
And it takes a
short minute or less.
And it have now created this
console.code
that workspace file. Which includes
those projects.
But also, it would actually be nice to
see what it contains.
So, let's
do
use this command.
The map command. It's
useful for visualizing what's in it. It
creates a markdown file using mermaid.
And we can actually preview it. And as
you can see here
what we have in this project is a
console base
where we have both console and inventory
and console sales.
That both depends on the base and then
we have console dashboard on the top
that uses two others.
Before, when we compile BC apps, we
would compile all the apps sequential.
We would try to figure out how the
compilation graph
was depend using dependencies and BC
helper.
This is now built into a new tool called
workspace compile.
Workspace compile can be directed or is
taking a
a [snorts] workspace
file as an input and then it
computes the most efficient compilation
graph
for compiling this workspace.
>> [snorts]
>> And let us do that.
Let's go down here.
And that command is called workspace
compile.
And it simply takes the
workspace I just created as the input.
And then it starts doing compilation.
And it figures out and you can see down
here right now it's compiling two
projects in parallel and now it's
compiling one.
So,
it realized that it has to compile the
base first and then it can actually
compile sales and inventory in parallel.
And at the end it compiled the
dashboard.
All of that
was computed as a large dependency graph
and then it just started from the bottom
and compile everything.
Using that one, we see huge gains. I
will get back to that in a second
because I also want to highlight another
new command
we have which is the is simple only.
It's also something that we use in the
AL Go for GitHub pipelines. It's used to
figure out whether an app file is a
simple only app file or it's a app file
that also contains everything else.
In this case, the ones I have just
created contains everything, but let's
just test and see if it's true.
I'm using the console base, calling that
and it's
as we
already knew, it's not a simple only.
And remember in my
directory app.prop.json
file, I included the runtime and set
that to runtime 16.
That's also something new.
I can actually use the
the the the the props file to also
specify the runtime and you can see here
it correctly
added the runtime 16 to the manifest.
These is some preliminary measurements
on how much we will gain by using this
when compiling the our BC apps repo.
We are using AL Go
as the driver for this.
And the as you can see the baseline is
currently just below 2 hours.
The timing here shows
with using different number of
processes.
And if I use four, which is the maximum
that you can use in a GitHub runner,
standard GitHub runner, it gets down to
26 minutes.
Which is I mean a reduction of 75%.
It turns out there's a I mean there's a
difference between the 50 minutes here
with one and the AL Go, but that's also
because the workspace compile actually
do all the orchestration where in AL Go
today, we use the BC container container
helper to do a lot of the
which what can I compile now on the
orchestration and what have you.
So, we expect to
use this
internally where we can because this is
very huge gain in utilizing our
hardware.
If you are using AL Go for GitHub
already,
you will get this for free and you can
just use as do as you're used to.
If not, you can use the tool in your own
pipelines to improve them.
Let's turn our attention to AI and I'd
like to welcome one of our very
experienced engineers, Arthur.
Tell me, Arthur, what's your perspective
on AL development at AI?
Thank you, Stefan. If I have to describe
my experience in a few words, I would
say it is about the changing mindset.
So, what I do nowadays is I I simply
spend less time writing low-level syntax
and more time describing how system
should behave. What should be the right
outcome. And what is equally important
is exactly what system should not do.
Um so, for me producing the code is kind
of not longer like the bottleneck,
right? But making sure it's correct,
secure and easy to maintain, that is
what is really important. And um
that is responsibility still on us, on
developers. It's not on the tool.
Um and the way I I I treat the
AI-generated code, it is a draft for me.
So, whenever I get the draft and
whatever you get the draft,
uh we review it, we correct direction,
we refine the prompt and we make sure
that the code is aligned with
architecture and with the standards.
Uh now, that was a bit theoretical. How
it's even related to Business Central
and AL language?
What is important here, it is not our
prompts that's used for compilation for
Business Central for our feature. It is
still good old AL language. But the
change of the mindset is exactly in the
way that previously I
wrote AL code and then I commit AL code.
Right now, there's a layer in the in the
beginning. So, I first describe the
intent, I get the draft and then
finally, I have a AL code generated. So,
AL becomes like a final record.
And even though if developers like me
describing functionality in prompts, the
final authoritative implementation of
Business Central is still lives in AL
code.
And what is important about AL?
AI here is not replacing AL. In fact, it
is
vice versa. AL suddenly becomes more
important. We can think of AI as an as
an intern. It's super productive, but if
you don't give it the rules, it will do
something let's say creative.
And AL basically is those rules. These
are constraints. And once AI is in the
loop, the good constraint is just a pure
gold.
And you can see all those constraint
exactly on the screen. And you know
them. You've been writing AL code for a
for a long time. And I need to admit
that I'm I'm writing my code with AI
different languages. And AL with great
capabilities is exactly perfect for for
the AI coding era.
Uh now, a few words about planning,
about the iterative approach. Nowadays,
I can quickly test my hypothesis. So, I
don't need to have a heavy upfront
planning. What I can do, I can build a
prototype within a day rather than a
week.
And that give me a possibility to
quickly build, learn from it, throw it
away and then actually start
making it smartly, iteratively, plan
mode, describing the proper architecture
and gradually modding adding more
features one by one with a proper test
animation. Exactly the same way how I
going to do this without AI.
Um
one of the real eye-openers for me is
the feedback loop. Once I define the
task for the agent and specify the
success criteria, and that could be for
example AL test, the agent can iterate
on solution and recover from failure
until the goal is achieved. That is
absolutely the greatest uh capability in
the AI coding era.
Um in this journey,
AI is definitely a collaborator. So, for
some for some reason, people think that
the general purpose of AI for software
engineering is writing the code.
But it also can help with brainstorming
ideas, planning, searching code base,
debugging, refactoring. A lot of use
cases and all of them are really
popular. But they require someone who
actually triggers the action. And that
someone is a software engineer like me
and you.
And the one who do not say, "Hey,
implement the feature for me. Be smart."
But rather use AI to research, find
proper references, create a plan and
then guide the agent towards the
execution. And if something goes wrong,
it's exactly it's a software engineer
who push it to the right direction. So,
you can think about AI as a new
colleague and just get started.
Doesn't really matter which coding agent
it is. Be curious and explore.
Over to you, Stefan. Thank you, Arthur.
Thank you. So, we still need to write
code. In the Business Central team,
we've been working on building tools to
help agents work with AL code. Blanca,
please help me get an overview of what
we've done in this release.
So, for better support of AL agentic
development, we have also added some new
AL tools both within the Visual Studio
code, which can be used by the GitHub
Copilot agent, and also through a
dedicated ALM
AL MCP server, which you can use outside
VS code with other agents such as Claude
or Codex, and also something that you
can use in your agentic pipelines.
So, first of all, let's start with
Visual Studio code.
So, here in my solution,
I already have You are pro- probably
already familiar with the GitHub Copilot
chat.
And here, if I check out the tools,
then you can see the AL extension
already provides some AL tools just out
of the box.
So, now the agent can build, debug, and
do many other things
as use these tools to solve more complex
problems.
So, for example, here I have an AL
project, and you can see I have some
diagnostics.
Uh there are some diagnostics about some
uh some of the dependency symbols that
are going to be obsoleted. So, I would
need to refactor this code, and instead
of doing that myself, I'm just going to
go ahead and outsource that outsource
that to my GitHub Copilot agent.
So, I'm just going to select tool fix
my diagnostics
and build.
All right. So, then after some time, you
will be able to see that the agent has
fixed all these diagnostics, and it has
also built the project for me.
If you want to see behind the scenes
what actually happened, then you can
just ask the agent.
And then here, you can see that it used
some of the two AL tools that the AL
extension provided. So, you can see that
it's very powerful to support different
scenarios, um and of course, you can
also include your own skills or agent
instructions to customize it to your
workspace, and
um solve more complex problems.
So, that was it for the
GitHub Copilot agent to use the AL
tools, but now, if you want to use uh
other agents like, for example, Claude,
then you will need the
ALM CP server.
This is a new MCP server that we have
added as part of this release, and to
get it, you can just simply download the
development tools
um in your command line, and then, if
you're using Claude, for example, in
this case, you can just add the ALM CP
um also with this command line, where
you specify your workspace path.
Um all of this is going to be
documented, so you don't need to worry
about it right now.
And then, if you go to to Claude in this
case, you can check out um
if your MCP is connected just like that.
As you can see, I have my ALM MCP
connected.
And then, uh I can also check it out.
And here, you can see that it has
multiple AL tools. They are not exactly
the same as in Visual Studio code, but
they do support most of the scenarios,
so you can use these also with a similar
scenarios in your um with your other
agents.
And then, a small note, you will see
here that when I'm downloaded the
development tools, I'm using the
pre-release flag.
This is because at the point of this
recording, uh this is only
available on the pre-release version.
Um at the point of when you see this
video, the ALM CP will be available also
just on the standard release version,
but uh in the future, if you want to
make sure you are using the latest um
if you want to see the latest features
or advancements that we're working on,
then you can always use the pre-release
flag to just test things out before they
actually come in in the release version.
Um and all of these scenarios was were
mostly focused on some sort of by coding
your AL solutions.
Um so, some human interaction in
[clears throat] the loop, but it might
also be the case where you might just
want to use some completely automated
agentic pipelines. And for this, the ALM
CP is very useful.
Um so, to showcase you how you can use
this for your agentic pipelines, I have
created one in GitHub, and here, you can
see I have uh
how the workflow looks like. So, I have
uh different steps where I use agents to
first of all compile
uh my extension and check if there are
any diagnostics and fix those. And then,
it also creates some tests and runs
those to ensure that there weren't any
regressions while doing so.
Um and then, if all goes correctly, then
it will open a PR, which I can review.
So, I'm basically automating through
agents the maintenance of my extensions.
If we look a bit
uh further down
uh this
um step, then you can see the step where
I'm using my agent. It is connected to
the ALM CP,
um and then, you can see how it's using
the different tools to, in this case,
compile, get the diagno- get the
diagnostics, and then fix my solution.
Um and it's doing the same with the
different steps.
And then, once that is done,
it creates a PR where I can see
um and review the changes done by the
agent.
So, as you can see, it's very powerful
how you can use the combination of
agents and AL tools to uh create a very
complex or to solve very complex
scenarios and tasks.
And that was it for the AL tools. Now,
um
onto you, Stefan.
Now, we've been building and testing AL
code. Let's look at something completely
different where we can use AI.
Troubleshooting.
Kelman, please guide us through what's
new in troubleshooting with AI.
The scenario is the following. An
external system sends a JSON file with
item codes.
Each entry is matched against the item
table.
If one is not found, an error is shown.
So, let's run this app.
Oops. It's failing. But it's failing at
a point it should not fail, because this
item
exists.
It is the office desk.
So, what went wrong?
Before debugging the code,
let's just go through what it does.
So, I have a method import from JSON,
which traverses a JSON file,
and for each JSON entry, it's calling
another procedure called process entry,
which is looking up in the item table
the JSON entry, and if it's not found,
an error is shown.
Pretty straightforward, so what went
wrong?
Let's attach to this process.
We have attached to the process.
Now, let's exercise the code.
It should break in the debugger. It
broke.
And now, instead of using the debugger
UI,
let's just
use Copilot and start prompting.
I'm going to prompt the following. The
AL debugger is paused on an error. Can
you investigate what went wrong?
This is going to take some time, but let
me explain what's going on.
Copilot has attached
to
the session
running the code,
and on that session, it's using the
Business Central troubleshooting MCP
server
to get stack frames and get variables.
Now, it goes through the variable
content, and let's see what it will be
its verdict.
It says it found the issue, but it's
still not finished, and now it finished.
So, what's the problem?
The problem is that the JSON entry item
code had leading space,
and this was the reason
why
looking it up has never found
an associated item code.
So,
it's suggesting the fix to delete the
entry character. It could have suggested
to trim it,
but nevertheless, this is a
acceptable solution, So, let's just keep
it.
The point is that it found a problem.
This was a data error.
A leading space issue.
And let's just step back for a second.
So, what happened here? I had a bug.
I couldn't see it by reading the code. I
attached the debugger, typed one
sentence, and waited a little bit, and
Copilot figured out what went wrong.
More,
it suggested a fix.
So, that said, can we use the MCP
troubleshooting server for something
else?
Can we use it for
analyzing performance problems
without doing a performance profiling
session?
Let's see.
I'm going to stop this debugging
session,
and I'm going to go to this code unit,
which is presenting a typical
performance problem. In this case,
CalcFields is called within a loop.
Let's see if
Copilot
can figure this out and suggest a fix
for this problem.
So, I have a unit test,
which is exercising this code unit.
Let's just run it.
Yep.
We are at the breakpoint. Now, let's
prompt start prompting again.
The prompt will be, "I am at a
breakpoint.
This test is very slow.
Can you analyze why?"
Still working.
It attached to the Business Central
troubleshooting server.
It's getting stack frames, getting
variables.
And let's see what will be the verdict.
Yep, confirmed. CalcFields is called
inside the repeat until loop. The root
cause,
yeah, it found very nicely the root
cause. And then it suggests a fix. Call
SetAutoCalcFields before FindSet.
Let's just accept this. This is a
correct fix.
And that's it.
Now we have a more performant code.
Let's just summarize what we have seen
here.
So, we have a completely new MCP server
for Business Central troubleshooting
server, which runs in an NST. And what
it does, it exposes the debug runtime to
GitHub Copilot.
It's very important to note that you can
invoke this while at a breakpoint.
But, at a breakpoint, Copilot
can inspect the full call stack.
You can uh you can prompt, "Give me the
stack at frame zero." Or, "Give me the
stack at frame one." And you will get
it.
It can read variables across all stack
frames or given stack frame. You can
prompt, "Give me all variables
at frame one or frame zero." Or, you can
do
you know, you can say, "What was the
variable X at frame one, and what
happened with it at frame two?"
You can fetch relevant AL source code
for a given frame.
More,
you can add breakpoints by object name
or ID and type,
plus a line number,
which is very helpful if you want
Copilot to govern you
through a debugging session.
The experience,
ask Copilot a single question,
it analyzes the entire execution
context, it identifies the root cause,
and helps you move forward without
touching the debugger UI.
Thank you very much. Troubleshooting and
building code with AI is great. And now
you can also design
and code agents for Business Central.
Check out all of these videos to help
you get started on building agents in
Business Central.
As always, check out the latest changes
in the change log, and try out the
pre-release for any upcoming changes and
addition to the developer experience.
This marks the end of this presentation.
I want to thank all my co-presenters for
sharing what's new in AL in this
release.
We are excited about the AI and all the
future things it brings, and looking
forward to hearing about all your future
development. Thank you for watching.